Dorothy Clark Collection, 1849-1983
Avery Memorial Association
Dorothy Clark Collection, 1849-1983
Clark, Dorothy Avery
Coll. 3
.5 linear feet; 2 boxes
Avery Memorial Association
The collection comprises material collected by Dorothy representing her line of the Amos Avery branch of the Groton Avery family. Material related to Oliver Perry Avery and his children figure prominently in the material that Clark gathered over the years.
Restrictions
Collection open for research by appointment only.
Acquisition Information
Donated in 2008 by Carolyn Clark in Memory of her mother Dorothy Clark.
Biography
Dorothy Crary Avery Clark (1920-2003) was born in Norwich, Connecticut, the daughter of Andrew Meech Avery (1884-1969), and Goldie Davis. Her father was descended from Amos Avery (1774-1840) and Dorothy Crary Avery (1759-1852) of Preston. Clark married George Pendleton Clark (1919-2007) in 1942. The couple lived in Ledyard and had two children, Delia Ellen Clark (born in 1949, lost at sea in 1987) and Carolyn Clark (1951-2011).
Avery family history was one of Dorothy Clark's interests, and material she collected related for the most part to her father Andrew Meech Avery's family. He had four half-siblings, Oliver Perry Avery (1871-1959). Delia Avery Southworth (1855-1910), Amos Avery (1868-1933) and Andrew Hewitt Avery (born and died 1876). Clark's collection has a number of items related to Oliver Perry Avery and his sons. (Dr.) Oliver Perry Avery was born in North Stonington, but spent most of his life outside of Connecticut as a Congregational pastor; he died in Claremont California. He had three children, Perry Dickinson Avery (1904-1990), R. Stanton Avery (1907-1997) and Martha Avery Vanderveen (1917-2013). R. Stanton Avery was the inventor of the self-sticking label and founded what became the Avery Dennison Company.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Dorothy Clark Collection includes original documents and photocopies related to the Amos Avery branch of the Groton Avery family. Much of the material relates to Oliver Perry Avery and his sons, Perry Dickinson Avery and R. Stanton Avery. Among the items are booklets on poetry and Preston cabinet makers, correspondence, a typed copy of Andrew Avery's diary, magazine articles by or about the Averys, particularly R. Stanton Avery, Avery International annual reports and newspaper clippings. It also includes information about the drowning of Delia Avery (1813-1849), daughter of Amos Avery, and a memorial book for Clark's mother, Goldie B. Avery.
Arrangement
Records are arranged in folders and housed in two boxes.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Avery family; Avery, Oliver Perry; Avery, Perry Dickinson; Avery, R. Stanton, 1907-; Avery Dennison Corporation; Avery International; Businessmen; Clergy; Inventors; Annual reports; Articles; Clippings; Correspondence; Diaries; Photographs; Poetry; Stationery
Related Collections
A Delia Avery Southworth drawing and a Delia Avery sampler are displayed on the wall in the upstairs master bedroom. An Amos Avery Bible is in a display case.
- Inventory
  - AMA.2008.352.01-.02, undated; Booklets of poetry from Perry Dickinson Avery; Printing press saga. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - AMA.2008.366.01-.09, undated; Avery International Labels; unmarked stationary for R. Stanton Avery. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - AMA.2008.370.01-.011, undated; Meech-Clark-Avery Genealogy. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - AMA.2008.371-374, 1980; Brochures for 1980 reenactment, Ledyard tours of house, Nathan Lester House. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - AMA.2008.375, undated; Typed copy of the diary of Andrew Avery, 1879. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - AMA.2008.377.01-.03, undated; Photocopy of information about Delia Avery, including her death in a boating accident on the Hudson River; also a letter about donating a picture of her (picture is AMA.2007.346) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - AMA.2008.380.01-.26, undated; Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - AMA.2008.381.01-.011, undated; Clark family genealogy. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - AMA.2008.383.01-.011, undated; Items related to Avery Memorial Association, cemetery, Avery Memorial Association annual meeting. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - AMA.2008.385.01.-.04, undated; Copies of early documents, some related to Parke Avery and Revolutionary War payment. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - AMA.2008.386.01-.57, undated; Large envelope of cards. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - AMA.2008.358, 1953; The Lapidary Journal from August 1953 with article called "From Black to Pastel Blue" written by Rev. Oliver Perry Avery. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - AMA.2008.360, undated; Booklet about Preston Cabinetmakers that contains article about John Avery. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - AMA.2008.361, 1976; Engineering and Science, 1976, containing article about R. Stanton Avery. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - AMA.2008.362, 1977; Annual report for Avery International, 1977, R. Stanton Avery. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - AMA.2008.363, 1983; Annual report of Avery International, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - AMA.2008.364, undated; Holiday Inn Companion magazine with article about Avery Island and Tabasco sauce (company located on Avery Island, branch of Avery business). (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - AMA.2008.365, 1966; Article about R. Stanton Avery in Newsweek, 1966. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - AMA.2008.367, 1962; Annual report for Avery International, 1982, R. Stanton Avery. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - AMA.2008.368, 1973; Package Engineering magazine, 1973, with R. Stanton Avery's photo on cover, article about Avery. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - AMA.2008.369, undated; Holland Herald magazine with article about R. Stanton Avery and Perry Avery's printing company with extra copies. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - AMA.2008.376.01-.018, undated; Goldie B. Avery newspaper clippings, cards, photos, memorial book. (Box 2, Folder 11)